Empresses in the Palace—the Legend of Zhen Huan
Adopted from the novel by Liu Lian Zi
[contact translators] carsenwei@yahoo.com
[subtitles subscription] liberapay.com/ZHZSubbers
Theme: Unfortunate Love
Perturbed by the thoughts on my mind
no matter how hard I try to sever my love.
I could give away my crown for the beauty by my side,
but the wheel of fortune turns weals into woes,
and woes into weals.
No one is the master of their own destiny,
the vicissitudes throughout their life.
For the lovers of all time,
who can break the spell of romance?
I could give away my crown for the beauty by my side,
but the wheel of fortune turns weals into woes,
and woes into weals.
No one is the master of their own destiny,
the vicissitudes throughout their life.
For the lovers of all time,
who can break the spell of romance?
Who can break the spell of romance?
[contact translators] carsenwei@yahoo.com
[subtitles subscription] liberapay.com/ZHZSubbers
Lady Sourire， Why did you come here in the deep frosty night?
It 's just because of the heavy frost at night that Lingrong is hard to come alone, so I came with her.
Lady Sourire is very good at playing Guqin. I invited her for fear that my singing would be monotonous
Singing accompanied by the sound of Guqin is naturally the best.
It must be a lot of trouble for Lady Sourire.
What songs do you like to listen to, Your Highness?
It's a wonderful night, so sing an affectionate song.
As sunlight streams through the bedside folding screen
her hair at the temples curls over her snow-white cheeks.
Sleepily she paints her eyebrows slim
Taking her time to dress and rinse
When she puts on a flower between mirrors, it’s hard to tell her face from the flower.
The new patch on her brocade vest
is two love birds in gold thread.
Two love birds in gold thread.
The song is very good, but I did not hear the affection.
Aren't you play at me?
Although this song doesn't directly describe the love of men and women, each sentence of this song expresses the joy of women after she fell in love.
And the two love birds also symbolize conjugal love.
So why aren't there the affection in your singing?
Is it because you see His Majesty with me, which makes you unhappy, and you can't sing well, too?
Your Highness, Attendant An had a chill in the morning, so she has a sore throat.
What a coincidence!
In the past few days Attendant An has sang to His Majesty all night long. Why does she have a sore throat today?
Song zhi
Yes.
Bring Attendant An a glass of sweet rose liquor.
This wine will keep you out of the cold and you can go on singing.
Ok.
Your Highness, I can't drink sweet or pungency things in the process of singing.
You can't sing songs or even drink.
By rights, it's His Majesty ask you to come here. You can look down upon me, but His Majesty...
Drink it since Consort Fleur awards it to you.
Yes.
what's wrong? Are you alright?
Your Majesty, Your Highness.
It is certainly beautiful when the zither is paired with a beautiful voice.
However, it can also be quite elegant when the zither is paired with words spoken.
Will Your Majesty allow me?
Good.
Yes.
[Carsen: this poem has several translations online already, though I wasn't sure if I should just copy/paste them in here.]
The clouds form various shapes; the shooting star carries various sorrows.
The Cowherd sliently wades through the boundless Milky Way.
He meets the Weaver Girl amidst the golden wind and the jade like dew.
A meeting that surpasses that of many humanly due.
The tender love flows like the water; and this beautiful moment is like a dream.
Looking back at the magpie bridge would be a hard thing to do.
If the two hearts are united forever,
why do the two persons need to stay together forever?
Lady Sourire is such an intellectual.
Alright. His Majesty and I are getting tired.
Thank you for your hard work.
Zhou NingHai
Yes, Your Majesty.
Please escort their leave.
Yes.
Thank you.
Go ahead.
Your Majesty.
It is getting late.
Time for bed.
Consort Fleur appreciates the My Ladies' hard work tonight.
Her Highness grants you these rewards.
I thank Her Highness.
If there are nothing else,
then I will take my leave. My Lady.
You are safe at our place,
if you feel like crying then let them out.
Zhen Huan, we are not circus performers.
How can she cheapen us like this?
What is this jade bracelet she gave us.
Such nonesense.
She thinks I'm only here to sing? She even rewards us!
My Lady!
My Lady. It's okay to be mad.
But if this breaks,
we won't know what kind of chaos it might cause.
Do not weep on it.
Your weak throat can't afford too much weeping. Take a drink.
Huan'er, you could have avoided this schemed scorn if I had went alone.
But, thanks to your presence there,
and His Majesty's favor on you,
otherwise she would have imposed more torture on me.
His Majesty's reliance on Nian Gengyao's ability
raises Consort Fleur's pride.
For the sake of a peaceful relationship,
there is little hope that Consort Fleur
would be punished by His Majesty.
I dearly wish Nian Gengyao is as far as possible.
Consort Fleur is too arrogant.
It won't be do ne by words.
Consort Fleur has accompanied His Majesty for a long time.
This intimacy would maintain,
as long as Nian Gengyao is favored.
I went to the Palace of Earthly Honor
to inform Your Majesty's sickness and
absence on the Celebration of Chrysanthemum.
Xiao-Xiazi told me that
Nobel Lady Sourire and Attendant An were performing for Consort Fleur's recreation.
So, I stayed to look on.
When both of them finished and walked out,
they seemed really composed.
I have already learned the composure
in Noble Lady Sourire's character.
But, I haven't expected that Attendant An would have the composure.
I should have paid more attention to her before.
Possibly she was only too cautious to show her resentment in public than in her palace.
Being composed in public eyes is good enough.
Consort Fleur has indulged her arrogance too much,
stepping on other's dignity.
Her ending would result from her behavior.
Anyway, Attendant An's behavior
is a surprise to me.
Here. This way.
I am here.
These plum blossoms are the best ones.
Be careful, My Lady. You cannot catch me.
Come on if you can catch me.
Take care, My Lady.
You won't catch me!
You can try!
My Lady, you should wear warmer clothes.
It's cold outside, snowing.
Listen to it. What a happy laughter!
I haven't heard such laughter for a long time.
Noble Lady Sourire and Attendant An have sent here bunches of coal.
I shall heat the rooms.
Whether the palace is warm doesn't matter,
as the warmth on the body would never reach my frozen heart.
My Lady, you are back.
You come back in such a short time from the white plum blossom s in the courtyard.
I got a little dizzy from gazing at the snow.
Si Lang had good intentions to plant white plum blossoms in the courtyard
But the white blossoms would be concealed from observation by snow.
It shouldn't bother you.
If you prefer red plum blossoms,
I would order the red plum blossoms transplanted in your palace
from the Garden of Leaning Plums.
It was you who ordered me to focus on doing transcription.
Now you are talking to break my concentration.
You can't make such a fun!
Blame on my talks for your absent mind.
If I hadn't lost the Go game with you just now,
I would be free from your punishment now.
Si Lang's words carries such weight
that your promise must be as solid as stones.
All right.
Huan Huan is here sewing Si Lang's winter clothes for your celebration.
It's not about my promise.
Just for your sewing,
I would like to copy it three times.
Si Lang, this is what you said,
to copy out all the plum chanting poems for me.
Do not go back on your words.
You pasted transparent papers on this window.
When the snow outside shines through,
it is brighter than the Hall of Mental Cultivation.
I don't like the room to be dim.
Besides, the candles are lit when it rains or snows.
It is smelly, and it's also too wasteful.
You are quite frugal.
Once winter arrives,
the use of candlelight in the harem alone has increased a lot.
Although not a large amount,
it is ultimately an expense.
That’s out of my small-mindedness.
It’s unexpected to be valued by Your Majesty.
When I meet the Empress,
I will tell her this method
to save every penny in the harem.
It's almost the end of the year.
If we can save some money to set up a porridge factory
to relieve the poor, it is also doing good works.
Right, then tell the Empress to do it.
Peace to Lady Chun.
Where is Sister Sourire?
Inside the chamber.
My Lady, His Majesty is also inside, My Lady…
Sister Sourire, Sister Sourire.
Chun’er is here.
Peace to Your Majesty.
Sister, have a look at
these red plum blossoms I picked for you. Are them pretty?
Yes, they are pretty.
Sister, it's so warm here.
It's freezing outside.
Quickly warm yourself by the fire.
Your Majesty,
are the red plum blossoms pretty?
Your sister was just talking about red plum,
and then you came.
Well, I know my sister best.
Attendant Chun seems to have grown a lot.
Your Majesty, you forget that,
after a year, I will reach the age of 17.
Don't just talk.
Quickly wipe the snow off.
Later you catch a cold,
do not cry when taking medicine.
Don’t hold the blossoms.
Get them arranged in a vase.
Jinxi.
Sister, don't you have a white porcelain vase there?
It is the best one to arrange red plum blossom.
You are good at picking plum blossom.
They are still in bud.
There are days to put forth their blossoms.
I like that color,
which makes our hearts warm.
I think of Sister so much.
What will Sister reward me?
There is nothing else.
Try some new cakes made by the kitchenette.
Great. There is nothing better than that.
Thanks to you, I will have something to eat.
Otherwise, your Sister Sourire will just leave me with an empty stomach.
That’s not true.
My Sister values Your Majesty most.
If Sister leaves Your Majesty with an empty stomach,
it must be Your Majesty staring at Sister,
having even no time to eat.
You see, how sharp-toothed she is.
It must have been learned from you.
Just eat. The food cannot occupy Your Majesty’s mouth.
I am not the Emperor today.
I think only of being the childe of an ordinary rich family.
Can’t I be a little bit garrulous?
I dare not to order about the Emperor,
but it is easy enough to order about a childe.
If these poems cannot be copied out,
no dinner will be served.
You see, is your Sister Sourire high-handed?
She is My Sister, and naturally I do not feel overbearing.
You have to grind the ink, otherwise I will not write.
Originally, I wonder
why am I so familiar with the scene
when Your Majesty and Sister are together.
Now I see, my elder sister and
brother-in-law at home are also like this.
One grinds the ink, and the other writes.
You ate too many snacks.
Come on. Drink some water.
Why not let her finish?
Go ahead.
Your Majesty just likes to listening to these playful words.
Formerly, my elder sister and her husband get along very well though they do not talk much.
My mother called it
Hmm
"Happiness in the Boudoir".
Where did you hear these jocular words at such a young age?
These words are just nonsense.
Your Majesty are still indulging her.
Your Majesty, do you think I am talking nonsense?
Of course not.
Your words are extremely brilliant.
HuanHuan(Nickname of ZhenHuan) and I should be like what you said.
My Lady,
We are entering the Hall of Mental Cultivation in a moment.
Please do not be afraid.
It's my first time that I see such a risible Lady like you though I have been servicing so many Ladies.
Slow down. Slow down.
At Sourire's, I saw she used Ming paper on the window, saving much money for candles and lights.
What do you think?
In the long winter in Beijing,
Noble Lady Sourire's method is very useful.
It is good to save some money as we need money everywhere in the year end.
I always thought her intelligence and scholarship was in poetry and literature,
but ignored her talent for managing the affairs.
It is I who underestimated her.
Noble Lady Sourire is very smart,
thus learn new things easily.
What 's more precious is her kindness
as she wants to open food relief center using the money saved.
She can do great things in the future.
I heard that Your Majesty convened Attendant Chun last night.
You reviewed the log of Attendance Services?
Attendant Chun has been in the harem for two years
and has turned to a big girl.
I remembered that she had a sweet tooth
and loved to dress in bright colors.
So I sent some bright clothes in the morning.
She is childlike and thus flirtatious more or less.
It's good to be flirtatious for a small girl.
But now she is truly a concubine
and should at least be dignified and generous.
Unlike some people who always make mischief and upset me, She is candid and lovely.
Your Majesty, Zhang Tingyu is here.
Let him wait for a moment.
Yes.
I bid Your Majesty goodbye.
Is everything alright for Nian Gengyao?
He is really busy with entertaining guests.
He is sure to have some old friends in Beijing.
Your Majesty, please excuse my bluntness.
Those guests are his subordinates.
He didn't entertain any other officials at all.
Say.
During his trip in Beijing
he ordered that the Capitain Leader Fan Shijie,
Governor-General Li Weijun
kneel to meet him and send him off.
He had a really ostentatious occasion when arriving in Beijing.
Officials below the Prince kneeled to meet him
while he was calmly on the horse, and even didn't look at them.
He was so arrogant and conceited that makes people feel fear and idignated.
Did it really happen like that.
I dare not talk tactlessly.
As Nian Gengyao returned with glory and fame after victory,
this kind of excessive pride was understandable. I will remind him.
Then I will be relieved hearing Your Majesty’s words.
You, the Ministry of Revenue are burdened with too much work.
As Nian Gengyao is familiar with border affairs,
to some extend you can negotiate with him.
But remember, just negotiate.
If his disciples are not behaving themselves,
domineering, or involved in provocations,
you can remonstrate in the memorandum with no hesitation.
I will definitely punish them and never tolerate.
The lunar new year is around the corner.
Has the year-end bonus arrived?
Yes.
But sounds came from The Household Department,
that His Majesty gave orders on reducing expenses.
So this year’s bonus is only half of those before.
It has been my convention to give a generous reward to the servants.
Even a double amount is still short, not to mention a half cut.
Isn’t it a drop in the ocean?
I couldn’t agree more. Unlike before,
General-in-Chief will spend this lunar new year in the capital.
We have to give out more rewards.
If you want others’ loyalty,
you should have prestige
and His Majesty’s fondness.
Most importantly,
only rewards can push them serving you truly.
Your Highness can ask some from General-in-Chief maybe.
These years
brother kept giving me overt and covert financial support.
With this tiny amount of monthly stipend,
I can’t get through even ten days
But my family’s support can’t be a long-term policy.
Actually, Your Highness, there’s an option to earn some extra money.
What’s your idea?
It’s said that,
since General came back to the capital,
a lot of people have been eager to formally visit him.
But General is too busy to summon them.
They have been drowned in anxiety
without any access.
If Your Highness
are willing to deliver a few words to General for them,
they will know
how to pay Your Highness back naturally.
Really so easy?
The imperial examination aims at selecting talents.
These people volunteer themselves for bright prospects.
If there is really a qualified one among them
and the General recommends him to His Majesty,
Your Highness is also one of the contributors.
His Majesty forbids the harem to be involved in political affairs.
They want to visit my brother.
I can recommend them
To be selected or not, it’s up to him.
So bright, Your Highness.
My Lady, you have removed the stitches and corrected the sewing back and forth
for many times.
Why hasn’t it been finished till now?
It’s for His Majesty and should be done delicately.
My Lady, you have been coughing
since caught a cold some days before.
His Majesty hasn’t been here for many days, right?
More than a month.
His Majesty is either with Consort Fleur
or Lady Sourire.
Consort Fleur is in the limelight.
I can’t compete with her.
Yes. But when His Majesty is with Lady Sourire,
My Lady’s friend,
she should have reminded him to see you.
His Majesty didn’t come.
Maybe she didn’t mention.
I hear that His Majesty selected Attendant Chun.
She’s still lively and noisy
just like before since in favor.
I think His Majesty didn’t remember her perhaps.
It may be Her Majesty’s reminder.
She’s always kind like that.
She’s considerate, for everyone.
But Consort Fleur keeps bullying you.
Her Majesty can hardly take care of you in spite of her kindness.
My Lady, please take a good rest as soon as possible.
I will bring an imperial doctor early next morning.
All right. You can go now.
Yes.
Oh,
you don’t need to make bed for me today.
Yes.
Consort Fleur ...
Go to hell!
Peace and grace to Your Majesty.
All rise and take a seat.
I thank Your Majesty.
These days were cold and blowy.
It is kindly to have you two this early.
I was about to come with Lingrong.
Sadly she has caught cold and couldn't bear the windiness.
thus accompanied by Attendant Chun.
Attendant Chun is getting prettier.
Did the emperor treated you kindly?
His Majesty favored me a lot.
He ordered the the Imperial Kitchen to cook plenty of delicious pastries for me.
Good.
You are now a concubine of the emperor.
You shall place the emperor as the priority in your life.
are you clear?
Your Majesty, may I ask you for a tiny flavor?
Go ahead.
I want to live with Sourire.
I moved out to avoid the illness, since Sourire has been cured for such a long time.
I am willing to accompany her.
Living along in the Palace of Pearl Jade is a bit of lonely.
It will be my pleasure to have Attendant Chun by my side.
It is fabulous to move back
I would be peaceful if every concubine shares such close relationship as you two.
It is about to move away?
Who can dare broke the thing of Attendant Chun?
Attendant Chun is young but not dump.
How changed playing up to people of power in those few days!
Attendant Chun isn’t this kind of person.
She is only found of bustling and want to change a place to live.
I am too found of bustling and want to change a place to live.
Is it also that simple for me?
She takes advantage of the emperor’s favor
moved herself after begging the empress.
The Palace of Pearl Jade is small and far off.
couldn't compare to your palace.
It is widely acknowledged that His Majesty favored Consort Fleur and them
Vying for favor couldn't be more easier since they huddle together.
Attendant Chun and you entered the palace at the same time, both recommended by Lady Sourire.
You’d better consider why she invited Attendant Chun but not you.
Lingrong!
Why standing here in such a cold weather?
Since it was a mess out there, I went and have a look.
It is a nice place near the Palace of Pearl Jade, why do you want to move?
Sourire and I are both found of bustling, thus matches more
Indeed, the similar background, the similar personality.
Please go back and take care of your body.
Take your time.
All right.
My Lady, the empress came.
Invite Her Highness in.
May peace and grace be with Your Majesty.
Rise.
I thank Your Majesty.
I have heard that you’ve been coughing a lot these days.
After visiting Consort Honnête I dropped by you.
I just caught the wind-cold
coughing a little bit.
I bothered Your Highness to worry about me.
You are young. You ought to take care of yourself.
You must not to get into a plight like Consort Honnête.
That makes my heart ache.
Autumn.
This is the tribury Donge ejiao offered by viceroy of Shandong.
Your Highness herself didn‘t spare to use it.
telling me to leave it to My Lady.
I sincerely thank Your Highness for the good graces.
Your house(palace?) here is chill in the winter but stuffy in the summer.
Luckily the temperature is mild with the charcoal burning.
I remember when you firstly entered the palace
Consort Fleur arranged your residences
all by herself
It's hard to avoid negligence.
Don't be fussed.
I dare to demand more
with Your Highness's solicitude.
I am satisfied.
See, you are the modestest and politest one.
I like you from the bottom of my heart.
I care for you.
I'm worried about you being bullied
and coming to grief.
I won't suffer loss with Your Highness's grace.
Won't suffer loss?
See, your hands are freezing.
Here, lie down quickly.
What's this?
Your Majesty.
All of you, get out.
You must not speak nonsense.
Yes, Your Highness.
This jade necklace
I remebered Consort Fleur the jade to you
and Lady Sourire
One for each
You should have this jade necklace cursed.
Who on earth did you lie curese on?
Consort Fleur? Or Lady Sourire?
Your Highness.
Lady Sourire and I are just like sisters
I dare not to curse Lady Sourire granted that I died.
So you cursed Consort Fleur?
How dare you to curse Consort Fleur?
Why?
Your Highness, Consort Fleur insulted me in all measures.
She treated me as a servant.
I indeed...
Absurd！
I all along consider you smart and prudent.
not expecting such a stupidity of yours
You dare to curse others in the palace
I beg Your Highness's pardon for my stupidity.
Not only fatuous,
but there can be no greater folly than this as well
If it were seen by Consort Fleur
you would die a tragical death.
Such malefic sorcery just depends on the spirits.
But your weal and woe are in your own hands.
If the curses really do much,
people in the world don't need to use their brains
I was fatuous.
I don't care about how much you hate Consort Fleur
I just want to tell you
Instead of racking your brain to curse others,
you'd better ingratiate yourself with His Majesty
Your Highness, I admit my fault.
You dull girl!
Get it burned as though I saw nothing.
I sincerely thank Your Highness for the grace
You must be desolated being alone in the palace.
Even if you regard Lady Sourire as your sister
She cannot attend to your everything
because of her advancement
If you nurse a grievance afterwards,
Pour out to me your own bitterness.
Don't do such stupid things anymore.
I shall never forget the great grace
Your Highness bestowed upon me
Fine. Raise, raise. It's cold on the floor.
You should be grateful to the one who told me this.
I wouldn’t have known it if she didn't.
I humbly ask Your Highness who she is?
Undoubtedly, she is your sister.
She didn't mean it.
She had no choice.
I have ordered her that this secret shall never be known by anyone else.
Is she Sourire?
Stop asking!
Your priority is to strengthen your body and everything would become easy.
I bid Your Highness goodbye.
My Lady, it’s time for medicine.
My Lady……
My Lady!
Traitor!
I don’t know what I have done wrong.
But punish me if so!
But I’m never a traitor!
My palace is only cleaned up by you.
And you know the clearest what I have here!
How dare you still pretend it!
Please don’t be angry.
I did clean up your palace before.
But these days you don’t allow me to touch your bed.
I really have no idea If something is missing or not.
Besides, not only I could enter your palace.
Daisy also could.
If there’s really something missing, then she is suspectable as well.
Daisy?
Yes.
You said that you wanted thicker quilts when it got cold days ago.
It is Daisy who came to arrange it!
I stood for your order that your bed shall never be touched and asked her to leave it elsewhere.
Yes, I forgot her.
She is from Sourire’s palace.
Coua, stand up quickly and let me check your injury.
I don’t deserve it.
I’m to be blamed for hurting you so badly.
But Coua, I hurt you badly because you are my confidant.
The scariest thing to me is that you should be the traitor!
My Lady, I don’t have the nerve to do it.
I’m so relieved.
But I didn’t expect that it would be Daisy.
My Lady, do you suspect her?
She is from Sourire’s palace.
There’s no other possibility.
I thought that Sourire sent her only to take care of me.
But it turned out that she inserted a nail under my nose.
I recall that two 水獭服褂子 were offered as tributes from The Imperial Household Department.
Remember to take them to Concubine Estime.
One is for her, and the other let her secretly send to Meizhuang.
Yes, I will.
I was planning to check Meizhuang when Concubine Estime is in charge of supervision.
But Consort Fleur are keeping an eye so close that spares no one.
My Lady, please don’t worry.
Next year, when Spring starts, you could simply ask His Majesty to release her when he is happy.
Remember to warn the department when you are free
that Liubei must be caught.
Yes, my lady.
It's time to go, my lady.
I heard that the Empress Dowager would be present.
Even Lord XVII has been back.
It would be impolite to be late.
Let's go.
Your majesty, I went to the old-age path in Jiange and Zitong county during this trip.
And Dujiangyan (an ancient irrigation system).
And Du fu thatched cottage museum in Chengdu.
Did you visit the Thousand Buddha Crags?
I know your majesty was devout to the Buddha.
So I had worshiped them in succession.
I appreciate your filial piety.
The road to Shu is harder than tp climb the sky.
Hard of you on this trip.
Consort Fleur is in such gorgeous dressing today,
Even though I have a poor eye sight.
I still can feel the bright dazzles.
Your Majesty rewarded me a step swings (a kind of hair accessory used in old age).
I was thinking to choose some beautiful clothes
to correspond with it.
So I asked the Embroider Department to make some.
Good jewelry should go with good clothes.
The silk flower you wear, I guess,
is also priceless.
The silk flowers used to braid hair in palace are all made of textile,
which looks pretty but is easy to spoil.
So I prefer the gold thread densely woven
with precious stones through it.
It definitely looks nice but must cost a lot.
Thanks for your majesty's concern.
After all my family subsidizes me.
There's no waste of official capital.
If only everyone can have such a family like Consort Fleur!
Then there's no need to lead a frugal life
with very little monthly silver.
Thanks to my majesty's appreciation
to my parents' family.
You're Nian Gengyao's only sister.
What I reward to him,
he will definitely give it to you.
Your Majesty, it's time to take the medicine.
The imperial doctor is waiting for you.
My son,
I'm not feeling very well, I would like to leave first.
Take care of yourself, my mother.
Then I can put my mind at ease.
I bid Your Majesty goodbye.
This is the wine made by Lady Sourire.
Let's have a taste of it together.
The one is the osmanthus wine.
It was me and Lady Sourire
who picked flowers blossoming in this autumn to make this wine.
No wonder Your Majesty looks so proud.
It's our honor to have a taste.
It's a imperial feast which involves many lords.
The osmanthus wine is sweet but seems too ordinary.
If the guests are treated with the precious wine treasured in the palace,
they must feel the imperial demeanor.
The war in the northwest has just been quelled.
Even our majesty are very frugal.
The imperial harem should follow our majesty.
To replace the precious wine
with the osmanthus wine made the emperor himself
can not only show his majesty's trait of thrift,
but also make the imperial relationship closer.
There's no wrong that you advocate thrift.
But I heard that you have a pair of jade shoes which made of Shu silk
that is so luxurious.
I wonder if I'm honored enough
to have a look on it.
That's his majesty who rewarded it to sister Wan out of adoration.
Of course the more expensive and luxurious would be better.
Now that his majesty likes, then what else does not make sense?
Am I right? Your Majesty.
I appreciate your frankness the best.
What do you think? Lady Fucha?
You are right. I agree with you.
[contact translators] carsenwei@yahoo.com
[subtitles subscription] liberapay.com/ZHZSubbers
Theme: The Lonely Phoenix
[phoenix is the symbol of an empress]
I dimly recall the colorful blooms in every summer.
They are as distant as the autumn moon in the water.
He loved me with a volatile heart.
And before I knew it, we fell apart.
Behind me are the promises and longing.
Before me lie the flute and the zither.
I loved you with my body and soul
But you hurt me from head to toe.
My wish ran athwart
and I ended up a fool of my destiny.
My love was the wind-swept flowers from a tree.
A plum bloomed in winter hoping for a fruitful summer.
But the irresistible winds of destiny destroyed her wish.
You can hear the flapping of a phoenix
but you will never see it.
What you see is the falling leaves from the phoenix tree.
Two love birds in gold thread.